<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A short defence of the orders of the Church of England, as by law establish'd, against some scatter'd objections of Mr. Webster of Linne by a presbyter of the diocess of Norwich.</title>
            <author>Milbourne, Luke, 1649-1720.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 79 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50844</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2038</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15534</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12950982</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12950982</idno>
            <idno type="VID">95912</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50844)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 95912)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 720:31)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A short defence of the orders of the Church of England, as by law establish'd, against some scatter'd objections of Mr. Webster of Linne by a presbyter of the diocess of Norwich.</title>
                  <author>Milbourne, Luke, 1649-1720.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 35 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed, and are to be sold by Randal Taylor ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
                  <note>A reply to remarks by Webster in his translation of Assertio septem sacramentorum.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Webster, Thomas, b. 1646 or 7. --  Assertio septem sacramentorum.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Government.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:95912:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>IMPRIMATUR,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Liber cui Titulus <hi>[A Short Defence of the Orders of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>&amp;c.]</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>H. Maurice R<hi rend="sup">mo</hi> in X<hi rend="sup">to</hi> P.D. Willielmo Archep. Cant. a Sacris.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Oct. <hi>24. 1687.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:95912:1"/>
            <p>A Short Defence OF THE ORDERS OF THE <hi>Church of England,</hi> As by Law Eſtabliſh'd: Againſt ſome ſcatter'd Objections of Mr. <hi>Webſter</hi> of <hi>Linne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By a Presbyter of the Dioceſs of</hi> Norwich.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed, and are to be Sold by <hi>Randal Taylor,</hi> near <hi>Stationers-hall.</hi> MDCLXXXVIII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="objection">
            <pb facs="tcp:95912:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:95912:2"/>
            <head>The Objection againſt our Ordination in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as eſtabliſh'd by Law, according to my beſt Apprehenſion, is this.</head>
            <p>THat whereas our firſt <hi>Liturgies</hi> after the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation,</hi> in the Form preſcrib'd for the <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination of Biſhops, Prieſts and Deacons,</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed not the Biſhop ordaining to ſignifie in the words of Ordination, for the ſake of what <hi>Office</hi> the Perſons ordained were to receive the <hi>Holy Ghoſt;</hi> that Particular being ſince added, as it ſeems to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge a former Omiſſion, ſo it leaves a large Chaſme between thoſe <hi>Rightly and Canonically</hi> ordain'd, and thoſe who were not ſo, to the utter <hi>Nullity of our Orders;</hi> that <hi>Addition</hi> made to our late <hi>Rituals</hi> not being ſufficient to repair the former defect. For Inſtance; Tho <hi>Arch-biſhop Cranmer</hi> might be <hi>Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally ordain'd</hi> himſelf, and ſo might rightly ordain others; yet thoſe ſo ordain'd by him, or his fellow Biſhops ordaining <hi>Dr. Matthew Parker</hi> only by the <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective Reform'd Service-Book, Parker</hi> was really no Biſhop, and ſo thoſe afterwards ordain'd by him were no true Biſhops, Prieſts or Deacons. Becauſe <hi>none can confer that power on another, which he never had really in himſelf;</hi> which, if true, the whole <hi>Engliſh</hi> Hierarchy falls to the ground.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:95912:3"/>
            <head>Anſwer.</head>
            <p>THis Objection looks ſomewhat plauſibly at firſt, and had it any thing of real Weight in it, would be much more pertinent than the ſo often alledg'd and baffled <hi>Romance of the Nags-head Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> but if duly conſidered, has nothing of Solidity in it: For</p>
            <p n="1">1. It takes for granted what we deny, and what thoſe of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church upon their own Principles can never prove, <hi>viz. That Orders are a Sacrament: Three things, ſays</hi> Merbeſius, <hi>a late and well approv'd Writer of that Communion, ought to concur to the Being of a true Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tria ad veri Sacramenti eſſentiam con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currere debent, 1. Nempe Promiſſio Gratiae ex eo derivandae. 2. Signum a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquod ſenſibile cum praeſcriptâ verbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum formâ, quod veluti Medium ſeu Organum ad applicandum Promiſſionem adhibeatur. 3. Denique Divinum Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datum, quo Chriſtus hujuſmodi Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum, fidelibus vel omnibus vel ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quibus adminiſtrari juſſerit. <hi>Ben. Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heſ. Sum. Chriſt. p.</hi> 3. <hi>q.</hi> 4.</note> 
               <hi>Firſt, a Promiſe of Grace to be deriv'd from it: Secondly, ſome ſenſible Sign, with a preſcrib'd form of Words, which ſhould be made uſe of as a Mean or Inſtrument whereby to apply the Promiſe; and Thirdly, ſome Divine Command, by which Chriſt has enjoyn'd the adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſuch a Sacrament, either to the whole Body, or ſome particular member of the Faithful.</hi> Now it will be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream difficult to diſcover all theſe Circumſtances in that which they call the Sacrament of Orders: For ſhould we grant, that by them <hi>Grace is deriv'd to the Perſon Ordain'd,</hi> or ſhould we own a <hi>Command of Chriſt for the Collation of Orders,</hi> yet where's that <hi>ſet Form of words appointed by Chriſt himſelf for the Adminiſtration of this Sacrament.</hi> In Baptiſm we have the words of <hi>Inſtitution</hi> indeed, and thoſe retain'd throughout the Univerſal Church, without any conſiderable Variati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:95912:3"/>
In the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> we have the ſame general Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: But here we have a vaſt unaccountable diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between the <hi>Greeks</hi> and thoſe of the <hi>Roman Church,</hi> and again between the <hi>Ancient and Modern Church of Rome:</hi> Where yet we may reaſonably ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, they could not have differ'd ſo much, had our Saviour left any particular form of words for that Solemnity: If there were no form of words pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrib'd, then, according to the Rule before-cited, <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders can be no Sacrament,</hi> and <hi>the Church of England</hi> is as much at liberty to depart from the preſent Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, as that was to quit its own <hi>Ancient Rituals,</hi> or to vary from the <hi>Eaſtern,</hi> or any other <hi>Chriſtian Churches.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides, <hi>That Indelible Character,</hi> which is ſaid to be given in Orders, is a principal proof of their being a Sacrament; but it would be a very hard task to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile that Decree of <hi>Gregory</hi> the Seventh Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> of that name, with this notion of an Indelible Character. <hi>We following the ſteps of the holy Fathers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ordinationes iliorum qui ab Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municatis ſunt ordinati, Sanctorum Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trum ſequentes veſtigia, irritas fieri cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemus. <hi>Conc. Rom.</hi> 4. <hi>A.</hi> 1078. <hi>Lab. &amp; Coſſ. T.</hi> 10. <hi>p.</hi> 370.</note> 
               <hi>declare the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of thoſe who are ordain'd by Excommunicate Perſons to be void and of no effect.</hi> For if the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of Orders be indelible, Excommunication can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not obliterate it, nor make Orders conferr'd by the Excommunicate invalid. Nor will that fore-menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on'd Character agree very well with that Rule of <hi>Pope Coeleſtine</hi> the Firſt, given to the Biſhops of <hi>Vienne</hi> and <hi>Narbonne; Let no meer Lay-man, no Man that has been twice Married,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nullus ex Laicis, nullus Bigamus, nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus qui ſit viduae maritus aut fuerit, ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netur; &amp; ſiquae factae ſint ordinationes illicitae, removeantur, quonium ſtare non poſſunt. <hi>Concil. gen. T.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 1621.</note> 
               <hi>none who is or has been the Husband of a Widdow be put into holy Orders; or if any ſuch unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Ordinations have been made, let
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:95912:4"/>
them be taken away as ſuch which cannot ſtand good.</hi> Here again it's plain enough, That if the Character be as, ſuppos'd, Marrying twice, or marrying a Widdow, which can ſcarcely be proved Sins, cannot poſſibly expunge it; to which I might add the Anſwer of <hi>Leo the Firſt to the Enquiries of Ruſticus Biſhop of Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bonne,</hi> concerning ſuch as only <hi>pretended to be Biſhops,</hi> and thoſe ordain'd by them: Only this I conclude, <hi>That if the Judgment of a Biſhop of</hi> Rome <hi>be ſo Auguſt and Sacred as ſome would perſwade us, Orders imprint no Indelible Character upon the Soul, and conſequently are no Sacrament.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Signa, quum ad res divinas pertinent, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramenta ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellantur. <hi>Aug. Ep.</hi> 138. <hi>ad Marcellinum</hi> 2. <hi>Edit. Par.</hi> 1679.</note> For ſhould the Aſſertors of this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment fly to that trite Saying of St. <hi>Auguſtine, That Signs, when they are apply'd to Sacred Rites, are called Sacraments;</hi> that would weaken, not ſecure their Cauſe. But if Orders muſt be a Sacrament in the ſtricteſt ſenſe, I deſire that paſſage of <hi>Aquinas</hi> may be remembred, <hi>That ſince the Matter of Sacraments, in the ſenſible parts or outward ſigns of Sacraments are determined,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <p>Cúm determinata ſit Sacramentorum materia, determinatae ſcilicet ſenſibiles res, multó magis determinata eſſe debet verborum in Sacramentis forma. <hi>Aquin. Sum. p.</hi> 3. <hi>q.</hi> 60. <hi>a.</hi> 7.</p>
                  <p>Si mutatio materiae aut Formae Eſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alis ſeu Subſtantialis ſit, nullum efficitur Sacramentum. <hi>Suar. p.</hi> 3. <hi>T.</hi> 3. <hi>D.</hi> 2. <hi>ſ.</hi> 4.</p>
               </note> 
               <hi>much more ought the Form of words in Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments to be determin'd:</hi> And that of <hi>Suarez, If there be any change of the Matter, or of the Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential and Subſtantial Form, there is really no Sacrament.</hi> Which Paſſages, how they'll agree to thoſe things hereafter to be mentioned, may be left to every ordinary Conſiderer.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It cannot be imagin'd reaſonable, that thoſe Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons who diſpute ſo much among themſelves concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Eſſence of Orders,</hi> ſhould Cavil againſt our Church, as wanting any thing <hi>Eſſential</hi> in them; for common Senſe teaches thoſe, who will engage in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie with others, firſt to agree among themſelves
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:95912:4"/>
what the Subject of the Controverſie ſhall be. Now it's to be conſider'd, That whereas the Ancient Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> requir'd only <hi>Impoſition of the hands of Biſhops and Presbyters</hi> in Ordination; later years have added the Ceremony of expoſing the <hi>Chalice with Wine, and the Patten with an Hoſt upon is, to the touch of him who is conſecrated Prieſt,</hi> with theſe words, <hi>Receive thou Power to offer Sacrifices to God, and to celebrate Maſſes both for the living and the dead,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Accipe Poteſtatem offerre Sacrificium Deo, &amp; Miſſas celebrare tam pro vivis quám pro mortuis, in nomine Domini, Amen.</note> 
               <hi>in the name of God, Amen.</hi> And this laſt has almoſt juſtled the more ancient Ceremony out of doors; being grown into ſo great a Reputation, that <hi>Aquinas</hi> plainly concludes, <hi>That ſince the principal Action of the Prieſt is to Conſecrate the Body and Blood of Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cum Principalis Actus Sacerdotis ſit Corpus &amp; Sanguinem Chriſti conſecrare, rectè in ipsâ Calicis datione ſub certa verborum Formâ imprimitur Sacerdota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis character. <hi>Aq. Suppl. q.</hi> 37. <hi>a.</hi> 5.</note> 
               <hi>the Sacerdotal Character is truly imprinted in the delivery of the Chalice with a particular form of words:</hi> Which Concluſion of his he proves by this Argument,<note place="margin">Ejuſdem eſt Formam ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, &amp; Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriam de pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ximo praepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare ad For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam; unde E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopus in Collatione Ordinum duo facit, Praeparat enim Ordinandos ad Ordinis ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptionem, &amp; Ordinis poteſtatem tradit; Praeparat quidem in inſtruendo eos de proprio officio, &amp; aliquid circa eos operando, ut idonei ſint ad poteſtatem accipiendam: quae qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem praeparatio in tribus conſiſtit, ſcilicet Benedictione, manus Impoſitione &amp; Unctione; per Benedictionem Divinis obſequiis mancipantur, &amp; ideo benedictio omnibus datur; ſed per manus Impoſitionem datur plenitudo gratiae, per quam ad magna officia ſunt idonei, &amp; ideo ſolis Diaconibus &amp; Sacerdotibus fit manus Impoſitio, quia eis competit Diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio Sacramentorum, quamvis uni ſicut principali, &amp; alteri ſicut Miniſtro; ſed Unctione ad aliquod Sacramentum tractandum conſecrantur, &amp; ideo Unctio ſolis Sacerdotibus fit, qui propriis manibus Corpus Chriſti tangunt; ſicut etiam calix inungitur qui continet Sanguinem &amp; Patena quae continet Corpus, ſed poteſtatis collatio fit per hoc, quod da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur eis aliquid quod ad proprium actum pertinet: <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>That it belongs to the ſame Perſon to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the Form, and to prepare the Matter immediately for that Form. Whence in conferring Orders the Biſhop does two things; for he firſt prepares thoſe to be ordain'd for the ſuſception of Orders, and in the next place gives the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:95912:5"/>
Power belonging to the Order: He prepares them, both by inſtructing them concerning their proper offices, and by doing ſomewhat about them, whereby they may be fitted for the Reception of Power; which Preparation conſiſts in three things,</hi> viz. <hi>In the Benediction, in Impoſition of hands, and in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction: By the Benediction they are obliged to Divine Obedience, and therefore that is given to thoſe of all Orders; by Impoſition of hands is given the fulneſs of Grace, by which they are fitted for great Offices, and therefore only Deacons and Prieſts have hands impos'd upon them,</hi> (He might have added Biſhops; but here our Diſſenters agree with the Paraſites of <hi>Rome,</hi> that Biſhops are neither a diſtinct Order, nor of Divine Right) <hi>becauſe to them belongs the Diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Sacraments, tho to Prieſts as Principal, to the other but as Miniſters; but by <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction they are Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated to handling the Sacrament, and therefore it's gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven only to Prieſts, who touch the Body of Chriſt with their own hands, and both the Chalice which contains the Blood, and the Patten which holds the Body, are Anoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; but the Collation of their Power and Authority, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in delivering ſomething to them which belongs to their proper work.</hi> And whereas it's his ſecond Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or Objection againſt this Concluſion, <hi>That our Lord gave his Diſciples the Sacerdotal Power when he ſaid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dominus dedit Diſcipulis Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtatem Sacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotalem quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do dixit, Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipite Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Sanctum, quorum remi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeritis peccata, &amp;c. <hi>Joan.</hi> 20. Sed Spiritus Sanctus datur per Manûs Impoſitionem, ergo &amp; in ipsâ Manus Impoſitione imprimitur Character Ordinis—Reſpondit, Dominus Diſcipulis dedit Sacerdotalem poteſtatem, quantum ad Principalem actum, ante paſſionem in Coenâ, quando dixit, Accipite &amp; Manducate, unde ſubjunxit, Hoc facite in meam Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memorationem, ſed poſt Reſurrectionem dedit eis Poteſtatem Sacerdotalem, quantum ad actum ſecundarium, qui eſt ligare &amp; ſolvere. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Receive ye the Holy Ghoſt; whoſe Sins ye remit they are remitted,</hi> &amp;c. John 20. <hi>and the Holy Ghoſt is given by laying on of hands, that therefore the Character of Orders is impreſs'd by that Impoſition of hands:</hi> He
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:95912:5"/>
endeavours to anſwer it, but with abſurdity enough, <hi>That our Lord gave his Diſciples Sacerdotal Power; as to its Principal Act, before his Paſſion in his Supper, when he ſaid, Take and Eat; and therefore he ſubjoin'd, Do this in Remembrance of me: But after his Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he beſtow'd upon them Prieſtly power, only as to its Secondary or inferiour Act,</hi> i. e. <hi>as to the Power of bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and looſing, which was given,</hi> (as alledg'd in the Objection,) <hi>by Impoſition of hands.</hi> In which anſwer he perverts the ſenſe of our Saviours words, <hi>Take and Eat,</hi> by reſtraining them to the Apoſtles alone, whereas they were intended to all Believers: And he miſtakes the Evangelical ſtory; For tho St. <hi>John</hi> tells us of that Power of binding and looſing, as given af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Reſurrection, in the Chapter by him cited, <hi>v.</hi> 22, 23. Yet he might have found the ſame Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion given to all the Apoſtles, even before the Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of that Supper, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.18.</p>
            <p>But to paſs by ſuch ordinary miſtakes; The Deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of Pope <hi>Eugenius</hi> the Fourth, in that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Council of <hi>Florence,</hi> is very poſitive in the caſe; for enumerating the Sacraments receiv'd by the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, and giving ſome account of their Nature, for the Inſtruction of <hi>Armenians,</hi> he tells them, <hi>That the ſixth Sacrament is that of Orders, whoſe Matter that is, by the touching of which the Order is conferr'd;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sextum Sacramentum eſt Ordinis, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus Materia eſt illud per cujus traditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem confertur Ordo; ſicut Presbytera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus traditur per Calicis cum vino &amp; pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenae cum pane porrectionem; Forma Sacerdotii talis eſt, accipe poteſtatem offerendi, &amp;c. <hi>Concil. g. T.</hi> 13. <hi>p.</hi> 538.</note> 
               <hi>as the Order of Prieſthood is given by of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering the Chalice with Wine, and the Patten with Bread, to be touch'd by the perſon ordain'd; and the Form of Prieſthood is that, Receive thou Power to offer Sacrifice,</hi> &amp;c. To which Paſſage the formerly-cited <hi>Merbeſius</hi> gives a very trifling An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:95912:6"/>
That the Council of <hi>Florence</hi> (forſooth) did not determine this <hi>Conciliariter,</hi> or as a <hi>Matter of Faith and Dogmatically,</hi> but only at the rate of <hi>Common diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe,</hi> without telling whether the Patten or Chalice were the <hi>Eſſential,</hi> or only the <hi>Accidental</hi> matter of Orders; which is wholly Impertinent, and no way reconcileable to what follows in the Concluſion of that Decree, <hi>viz. Theſe things being thus explicated, the</hi> Armenian <hi>Orators, in their own name,</hi>
               <note place="margin">His omnibus explicatis Armenorum O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratores nomine ſuo &amp; ſui Patriarchae &amp; omnium Armenorum hoc ſaluberrimum Synodale Decretum, cum omnibus ſuis Capitulis, declarationibus, definitioni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, traditionibus, praeceptis &amp; ſtatutis, omnem que Doctrinam in ipsâ deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptam; nec non quicquid tenet &amp; docet Sancta ſedes Apoſtolica &amp; Romana Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſi, cum omnia devotione &amp; obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiâ acceptant, ſuſcipiunt &amp; amplectun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. <hi>P.</hi> 540.</note> 
               <hi>and in the name of their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch, and of all the</hi> Armenians, <hi>do with all Devotion and Obedience, ſubmit to, and embrace this moſt wholeſome Synodical Decree, with all its Canons, Declarations, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitions, Traditions, Precepts and Appointments, with all that Doctrine laid down in it; and whatſoever elſe that holy Apoſtolick See, and the</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>Church maintains and teaches.</hi> And to the ſame purpoſe, and almoſt in the ſame words ſpeaks Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal <hi>Pool,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Concil. T. <hi>14.</hi> p. <hi>1740.</hi>
               </note> our Country-man, in his Decree con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>Reduction</hi> of England <hi>to the</hi> Roman <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion.</hi> But notwithſtanding the Expreſſiveneſs of three ſuch very conſiderable Authorities, others of the ſame Communion have preſum'd to think otherwiſe, and to fix the Eſſence of Ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on only in <hi>Laying on of hands,</hi> without regard to any Form of Words whatſoever; declaring Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on of hands and Prayer to be the only <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient and Catholick Ceremonies,</hi> in the conferring of Holy Orders: So <hi>Durandus,</hi> giving an account of what conſtitutes a Prieſt, aſſures us, <hi>That, according to Canonical Tradition, when a Prieſt is
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:95912:6"/>
ordain'd, the Biſhop giving him his Bleſſing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Secundúm Canonicam traditionem, Presbyter cum Ordinatur, Epiſcopo cum benedicente &amp; manum benedictori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am ſupra caput ejus tenente, &amp; omnes Presbyteri qui adſunt, manus ſuas juxta manus Epiſcopi teneant, ſupra Caput illius Spiritum Sanctum invocantes, quae Manus impoſitio operum Sancti Spiritus exercitationem ſignificat. <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand. Rational. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 10.</note> 
               <hi>and holding that hand with which he gave the Bleſſing up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his head; all thoſe Prieſts who are preſent, lay their hands upon his head too, by the hands of the Biſhop, invoking the influences of the Holy Ghoſt upon him; which Impoſition of hands ſignifies the power of exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the gifts of the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> In which words, ſince he agrees ſo exactly with, as to tranſcribe the <hi>third Canon of the fourth Council of</hi> Carthage, I need not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat that again: It's true, he mentions afterwards the Ceremony of touching the Chalice and Patten, but of that only as <hi>additional or accidental, not Eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial.</hi> And <hi>Caſalius</hi> in his Book concerning <hi>Ancient Chriſtian Rites,</hi> tho he plainly determine Orders to be one of the ſeven Sacraments of the new Law, yet never mentions the touching the Veſſels, but only Impoſition of hands; which,<note place="margin">Ordo eſt Signaculum quoddam Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae, quo Spiritualis poteſtas traditur Ordinato—Impoſitio autem manuum confert gratiam &amp; cum effectu conſiſtit. <hi>Caſal. de vet. Chriſt. Rit. c.</hi> 26.</note> as he proves from Scripture, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers Grace, and has its due effects; and yet he gives us <hi>Aquinas his Definition</hi> of that pretended Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. The firſt <hi>Council</hi> held at <hi>Cologne</hi> in the year 1536. aſſerts the ſame Doctrine, <hi>That the Epiſcopal Office conſiſts chiefly in two things, the firſt of which is the laying on of hands,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epiſcopi munus in ducibus po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſſimum conſiſtit, 1. In Impoſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne manuum quae eſt Ordinum Eccleſiaſti corum col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latio, &amp; Inſtitutio Miniſtrorum—Poſtea vero—Impoſitio manuum eſt Oſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um per quod Intrant, qui Eccleſiarum gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernaculis admoventur. <hi>Conc. T.</hi> 14. <hi>p.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 3.</note> 
               <hi>which is the Collation of Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Orders, and the Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of Miniſters.</hi> And after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, <hi>Impoſition of hands is that Door by which thoſe are admitted, who are rais'd to the Government of the Church.</hi> So the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:95912:7"/>
Council at <hi>Mentz, Anno</hi> 1549. <hi>Let the Pariſh Prieſts teach their People,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In collatione Ordinum quae cum Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitione manuum velut viſibili ſigno tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditur, doceant Parochi, ritè ordinatis gratiam divinitùs conferri, quâ ad Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtica munera, ritè &amp; utiliter ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercenda, apti &amp; idonei efficiantur, &amp; quà rata ſint &amp; efficacia, quae à ritè ordinatis in Eccleſiâ, juxta Chriſti &amp; Eccleſiae Inſtitutionem geruntur. Hanc vero gratiam eſſe Ordinis &amp; Muneris, non Hominum aut perſonarum, nec ad cujuſquam privatam, ſed ad Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munem totius Eccleſiae utilitatem acco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modari. Ideoque in ritè ordinatis, ſive boni ſive mali ſint, efficacem eſſe, atque ita inter diſpares Miniſtros Domini no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtri dona ſemper aequalia ſemper bona &amp; ſacra permanere. <hi>Concil. T.</hi> 14. <hi>p.</hi> 679.</note> 
               <hi>That in the Collation of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, which are given by the Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of hands, as the viſible ſign, That Grace is conferr'd by Heaven upon thoſe who are regularly ordain'd, by which they are made apt and fit to exerciſe Offices in the Church du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and profitably, and by virtue of which thoſe Church Matters, which are managed by Men ordain'd accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Inſtitution of Chriſt and his Church, are rarified and made efficacious: That this Grace belongs not to the Perſon, but to the Office, and is accommodated, not to any Mans private, but to the publique benefit of the Church, and therefore is effectual in thoſe rightly or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain'd, be they good or bad; and therefore the gifts of our Lord, tho given to Miniſters very differently quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, are ſtill the ſame, always good and always holy.</hi> Which Doctrine perhaps even in ſome other particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, is not very agreeable to thoſe opinions eſpous'd by divers of the <hi>Roman</hi> Communion. I need not add here the Sentiments of <hi>Habertus</hi> and <hi>Goar,</hi> the learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Editors of the <hi>Greek Pontifical and Euchology,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to take notice of them afterwards: But I cannot well paſs by the Judgment of <hi>Bonus Merbeſius</hi> in the Caſe, who tho he take a great deal of pains to appear Neuter in it, yet apparently enough inclines to this, <hi>That the Eſſence of Orders conſiſts in this Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of hands,</hi> for which he refers us to ſeveral <hi>Texts of Scripture,</hi> ſeveral <hi>determinations of Councils</hi> and <hi>ſayings of the Greek Fathers;</hi> but there's nothing
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:95912:7"/>
more remarkable than what he alledges out of that learned Jeſuite <hi>Maldonate,</hi> who plainly, and without any heſitancy determines, <hi>That in conferring Orders, Impoſition of hands is not to be look'd on as an unneceſſary Ceremony,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <p>Impoſitio manuum non eſt habenda tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam Caeremonia non neceſſaria, ſed tanquam pars eſſentialis Sacramenti, idque tenendum videtur fide Catholica.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Quia in Scripturâ ubicunque fit mentio de ordinatione, declaratur per manuum Impoſitionem, &amp; videtur mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hi eſſe temerarium Scripturam deſerere &amp; conſectari Chimaeias, <hi>i. e.</hi> rationes naturales.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Quia veterem Eccleſiam nunquam ordinaſſe ſine Impoſitione manuum, ex omnibus Authoribus antiquis perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuum eſt, de Traditione autem Calicis, &amp; Hoſtiae nulla eſt apud eos mentio.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Quia videtur nimis durum eſſe, Caeremoniam, quam nobis perſpicuè tradent Apoſtoli, excludere à naturâ Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramenti, &amp; inducere illam de quâ nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la mentio fit in Scripturâ.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Quia hoc eſt labefacere totum Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentum &amp; victoriam concedere Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticis; nam ſi Impoſitio manuum non eſt eſſentialis Caeremonia; per quam hoc Sacramentum exhiberi debeat, non po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt probari ex Scripturis Ordinem eſſe Sacramentum. <hi>Merb. Sum. Chriſt. de Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cram. Ord. Diſp.</hi> 6.</p>
               </note> 
               <hi>but as an Eſſential part of that Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and that to him this ſeems a neceſſary point of the Catholick Faith;</hi> for which he gives theſe Reaſons,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Becauſe whereever Scripture mentions Ordination, it expreſſes it by Laying on of Hands, and it ſeem'd to him a Raſh thing to Deſert Scripture, and purſue Chimera's,</hi> i. e. <hi>meer Natural Reaſons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Becauſe it's evident by all Ancient Writers, that the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Church Ordained none but by Impoſition of Hands; but there is no mention at all made by any of them of touching the Chalice and Patten.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Becauſe it ſeems very abſurd, to exclude that Ceremony which was unqueſtionably deliver'd down to us by the Apoſtles from the Eſſence of the Sacrament, and to introduce another never ſo much as mention'd in Scripture.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Becauſe this were to ruine the whole Sacrament, and to give up the Victory to Hereticks; for if Impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Hands be not the Eſſential Ceremony whereby this Sacrament is to be exhibited, Orders can never be prov'd a Sacrament by Scripture:</hi> For whereas he ſeems to take it for granted, <hi>That the matter of every Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ought to be determin'd in Scripture;</hi> He urges it
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:95912:8"/>
well enough, <hi>That the Chalice and Patten not being ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken notice of there, that Ordinance, to which ſuch unſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Circumſtances are Eſſential, can be no Sacrament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this <hi>Merbeſius</hi> takes to be more <hi>Ancient and Catholick,</hi> though he acknowledges the other at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to be the <hi>more Common and Prevailing Opinion. Habertus</hi> makes <hi>Dominicus a Soto,</hi> a <hi>Spaniard,</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor to <hi>Charles the</hi> 5th. and preſent at <hi>the Council of</hi> Trent, to be the firſt Inventer of it, but without Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, ſince, as I have proved before, both <hi>Aquinas and the Florentine Council</hi> eſpous'd the ſame Abſurdity long before: Againſt it <hi>Merbeſius</hi> urges this Argument, <hi>If the Sacerdotal Grace be given by Impoſition of Hands,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Si per manuum Impoſitionem, datur gratia Sacerdotalis, illa ipſa Manuum Impoſitio Presbyteratus eſſentiam pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culdubio conſtituit; Atqui per manuum Impoſitionem datur; Ergo.</note> 
               <hi>then certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that Impoſition of Hands muſt conſtitute the Eſſence of the Sacerdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Order; but the firſt is true, therefore the laſt.</hi> This he proves from that of the Apoſtle to <hi>Timothy, Ep.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 6. and from the diſcourſes of <hi>Moring</hi> to that purpoſe; from the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſilence of all <hi>Ancient Ritualiſts,</hi> and from the particular ſilence of ſome of latter date, who indeed mention that <hi>Adjectitious Ceremony,</hi> but yet only as Accidental, and not Eſſential to Ordination: Nay, he draws in the <hi>Council of</hi> Trent it ſelf as an Abet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour of his Opinion, by that paſſage concerning <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction,</hi> where they tell us, <hi>That Biſhops or Prieſts Regularly Ordain'd by them, with the Impoſition of the Hands of the Presbytery,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Legitimi iſtius Sacramenti Miniſtri ſunt, aut Epiſcopi, aut Sacerdotes ab ipſis rite ordinati per Impoſitionem Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuum Presbyterii. <hi>Seſſ.</hi> 14. <hi>c.</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>are the only lawful Miniſters of that Sacrament.</hi> Thus we ſee the <hi>Diviſion</hi> of thoſe of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church among themſelves concerning this Matter; by which, according to their own Writers,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:95912:8"/>
they reduce themſelves to this <hi>Dilemma, Either to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine the touch of the Veſſels to be the Eſſence of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and conſequently Orders no Sacrament, or elſe to allow it's Eſſence to be Impoſition of Hands;</hi> which Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of Hands the <hi>Church of England,</hi> according to the Cuſtom of the <hi>Ancient <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Church,</hi> has ever us'd ſince the <hi>Reformation,</hi> though not believing Holy Orders ſo conferr'd to be a Sacrament.</p>
            <p>I might here take notice of that Conceipt of ſome of their Paraſitical Canoniſts, <hi>That the Biſhop of</hi> Rome <hi>has that Plerophory of Power in himſelf, that his bare word can make a compleat Prieſt or Biſhop without any Ceremony at all;</hi> which is fairly expos'd by the learned <hi>Arch-Biſhop of Spalato,</hi> as which,<note place="margin">Spalat. de Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publ. Eccleſ. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>4.</hi> ſ. <hi>19.</hi>
               </note> among other things ſufficiently proves Orders no Sacrament, unleſs we can have a <hi>Sacrament without either Matter or Form.</hi> To proceed then,</p>
            <p n="3">3. Seeing our Ordination is thus far Regular, we are to conſider, Whether thoſe words made uſe of in our eldeſt <hi>Reform'd Rituals</hi> are not ſignificant enough; Or, Whether that Form of conferring Orders, was not ſufficient to impart Sacerdotal Power to the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons Ordain'd: Now, that it may not be left unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termin'd by the Ordainers, what particular Offices any Perſons are Ordain'd to, the <hi>Arch-Deacon,</hi> as in the caſe of <hi>Deacons,</hi> ſo in that of Prieſts, ſpeaks thus openly to the Biſhop, <hi>Reverend Father in God, I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to You theſe Perſons to be admitted to the Order of Prieſthood;</hi> After ſeveral Intercurrent Queſtions, the Biſhop declares to the People, <hi>Good People, theſe be they whom we purpoſe, God willing, to receive this day to the Holy Office of Prieſthood,</hi> &amp;c. After which words, methinks there needs no plainer a deſignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to any Eccleſiaſtical Employ; Publick notice is given likewiſe in the Ordination of a Biſhop, that all
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:95912:9"/>
there preſent may know what Character he is to bear. After theſe things and ſome particular Queſtions pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to the Parties, and ſome Prayers put up to God; <hi>For a Prieſt,</hi> the Biſhop with the Prieſts then pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, lay their hands upon every particular Mans Head, The Biſhop uſing theſe words, <hi>Receive thou the Holy Ghoſt, whoſe ſins thou doſt remit they are remitted, and whoſe ſins thou doſt retain they are retained, &amp; be thou a Faithful Diſpencer of the word of God, and of his holy Sacraments, in the Name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> As for a Biſhop, the words whereby <hi>Matthew Parker</hi> in particular was ordain'd,<note place="margin">Vide Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrum Cantuar ad calcem ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Bramhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li Ep. Armach. ex Autogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pho publica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum.</note> were theſe; <hi>Take the Holy Ghoſt, and remember that Thou ſtir up the Grace of God, which is in thee, by Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of hands, for God hath not given us the Spirit of Fear, but of Power, and Love, and Soberneſs.</hi> If now an Imitation of the Apoſtles be valid, nothing can come nearer, to what Scripture tell us of them, than thoſe words in the Conſecration of a Biſhop: Nor any thing more agreeable to the Pattern of our Lord, in the Commiſſion he gave his Diſciples, than thoſe us'd in the Conſecration of a Prieſt. And where ſo publick an Advertiſement is given to the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, of what Office thoſe Conſecrated are appointed to, tho words to the ſame purpoſe may be repeated again, as in our later Books of Ordination, tho they may ſerve to illuſtrate the matter in hand more fully, yet there can be no ſuch neceſſity of them, as that the want of them ſhould invalidate the whole Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance: And as we have no Account in <hi>Antiquity,</hi> of any particular <hi>form of words</hi> appointed by our Saviour for the conferring of Orders; ſo we are aſſur'd that according to the moſt <hi>Antient Methods and Ordinals of the Church of</hi> Rome it ſelf, it's not the Words but the Impoſition of hands that's eſſential to Ordination.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:95912:9"/>Beſides, If the <hi>Church of</hi> Rome, in the Collation of Orders according to their lateſt <hi>Pontificals,</hi> do no more than we do, it muſt ſeem very unreaſonable to condemn us as Defective. What they do then in the Ordination of Prieſts, which I ſhall only Inſtance in at preſent is this, <hi>The Arch-deacon preſents thoſe to be</hi> Ordain'd to the Biſhop with theſe words, <hi>Moſt Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Father, our Holy Mother the Catholick Church, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires that You ordain theſe Deacons, here preſent, to the Burthen of Prieſthood,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <p>Archdiaconus praeſentat Ordinandos Pontifici, dicens—Reverendiſſime Pater, poſtulat ſancta mater Eccleſia Catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca, ut hos praeſentes Diaconos ad onus Presbyterii ordinetis—Quorum meritis Archdiacono teſtimonium exhibento, Pontifex annunciat Clero &amp; populo dicens—Quoniam fratres Chariſſimi, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>—&amp; poſtea—Horum ſiquidem Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aconorum in Presbyteros ordinandorum auxiliante Domino, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Poſt haec ſurgunt omnes, &amp; ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis coram Pontifice binis &amp; binis ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive genu flectionibus, Pontifex ſtans ante Faldiſtorium ſuum cum Mitra &amp; nullâ oratione, nulloque cantu premiſſis, imponit ſimul utramque manum ſuper caput cujuſlibet ordinandi ſucceſſivè, ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil dicens, idemque faciunt poſt eum omnes Sacerdotes qui adſunt.</p>
                  <p>Quo facto tam Pontifex quàm Sacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotes tenent manus dexteras extenſas ſuper illos, &amp; Pontifex ſtans dicit, Oremus fratres Chariſſimi, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>— &amp; poſtea precatur Exaudi nos quaeſumus Domine Deus noſter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>— Ut ſuper hos famulos ſuos quos ad Presbyterii manus elegit coeleſtia dona multiplicet, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Tum Pontifex claudit &amp; inungit manus cuilibet ſucceſſive, quas ſic conſecratas aliquis Miniſtrorum Pontificis albo panniculo lineo ſimul, <hi>viz.</hi> dextram ſuper ſiniſtram alligat. Omnium manibus unctis &amp; conſecratis Pontifex, tradit cuilibet ſucceſſive calicem cum vino &amp; aquá &amp; Patenam ſuperpoſitam cum Hoſtiá &amp; ipſi illam accipiunt inter indices &amp; medios Digitos &amp; Cappam Calicis &amp; patenam ſimul tangunt, Pontifice ſingulis dicen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, Accipe Poteſtatem, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Quo finito Pontifex cum Mitrâ ſedens ſuper Faldiſtorium ante medium altaris, impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit ambas manus ſuper capita ſingulorum coram eo genu flectentium, dicens cuilibet, Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipe Spiritum Sanctum, quorum remiſeris peccata remittuntur &amp; quorum retinueris re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenta ſunt. <hi>Pontif. Rom. in Ordin. Presb.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> 
               <hi>after the Arch-deacons atteſtation to their Merits, the Biſhop at large declares to the People his deſign to promote thoſe Deacons ſo preſented, to the Office of Prieſthood, requiring their teſtimony to their Converſation,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Then having given an Exhortation to the Perſons to be Ordain'd, when it's done, all ſtand up, and thoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd for Ordination kneel down ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſively by two and two, before the Biſhop. The Biſhop ſtanding before his Faldſtool with his Mitre on, without any Prayer or Anthem pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, puts, both his hands ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:95912:10"/>
upon the head of every one, not ſpeaking a word: After him all the Prieſts who are preſent do the ſame; which being done, the Biſhop and Prieſts together lay hands on them; and the Biſhop ſtanding, exhorts the people to pray to God to ſend his manifold gifts upon thoſe whom he has now call'd to the Prieſtly Office, (which very expreſſion intimates the Sacerdotal Character already imprinted) and the Prayer to that purpoſe follows. After ſeveral other Ceremonies and Prayers, the Biſhop having anointed their hands, and one of his Attendants having ty'd them together with a Linnen Fillet, he reaches out to them the Chalice with ſome Wine and Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in it, and the Patten with an Hoaſt upon it, which they take between their fore and middle fingers, touching the Bolle of the Chalice and Patten at the ſame time, when the Biſhop uſes thoſe words, Receive thou power,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And here Maſs being celebrated, the Ordain'd Communicate, but only in one kind, and ſtanding before the Altar, make a Confeſſion of their Faith in the words of the Apoſtles Creed; which when they have done, the Biſhop ſitting upon his Faldſtool, with his Mitre on, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the middle of the Altar, and they kneeling down before him, he puts his hands upon every one of their heads, ſaying to every one diſtinctly, Receive the Holy Ghoſt, whoſe ſins,</hi> &amp;c. Theſe are the moſt conſiderable Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances in ordaining a Prieſt of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> in all which if Impoſition of Hands only Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the <hi>Sacerdotal Character,</hi> and the touching of the Veſſels be only <hi>Novel and Adventitious,</hi> then it plainly follows, That the Biſhops of that Church in giving Holy Orders, do no more declare what parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Office that Impoſition of hands relates to, than the <hi>Church of England</hi> in her eldeſt <hi>Rituals</hi> ſince the <hi>Reformation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:95912:10"/>But if we examine things farther, we ſhall find them much more defective; for whereas by the <hi>Roman</hi> Rubrick, the Biſhop lays hands on the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain'd three ſeveral times, and the firſt time uſes no words at all; it's the concluſion of the formerly-cited <hi>Merbeſius</hi> (and he pretends to good company in it) that <hi>That firſt Impoſition of Hands that's in ſilence, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers the Prieſtly Character;</hi> which he proves by 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.14. <hi>Stir up the Gift which is in thee, and which was given thee by Propheſie, and by the Laying on of the hands of the Presbytery;</hi> where the Apoſtle reſolves Orders into that particular Action. Then telling us how general his Opinion is, he concludes, <hi>Therefore it's the firſt Impoſition of Hands, by which they are made Prieſts;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſta igitur prima Manuum Impoſitio, ea eſt per quam Sacerdotes efficiuntur, cum neque per ſecundam Manuum Impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem fiant Presbyteri ut vidimus, nec per tertiam cum illa in fine ordinationis factitari ſolet. <hi>Merb. de Sacr. Ord. D.</hi> 6. <hi>g.</hi> 52.</note> 
               <hi>ſince it's certain, they are neither made ſo by the ſecond laying on of Hands</hi> (the Exhortation annex'd to which, as I obſerv'd before, ſuppoſes the Prieſtly power already given) <hi>nor yet by the third, which is only us'd in the Concluſion of Ordination.</hi> From all which it ſeems very probable, That let our Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation be never ſo Imperfect, ſince we really uſe ſome Words at the inſtant of Impoſition of hands, and thoſe very pertinent and authentick, that Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance is at leaſt more compleat in our Church than in theirs, who lay on hands indeed, but declare nothing at all, either of their Reaſon for it, or their Meaning in it.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The greateſt Bigots of the <hi>Roman</hi> Communion never charge the <hi>Greeks</hi> (tho they account them <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> for the moſt part) with want of a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Prieſthood; yet their Rituals are certainly, <hi>by Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man rules,</hi> as defective as ours can be imagin'd. In
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:95912:11"/>
that Church, <hi>He who was a Deacon before, and now to be ordained Prieſt, being brought ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to preſcription before the Biſhop or Patriarch,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. Pontific. Gr. de Conſecr. Presbyt.</note> 
               <hi>the Patriarch makes the ſign of the Croſs three times upon his Head, when he fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his eyes upon the Holy Table, and kneeling on both knees on the ſtep, the Chancellor calls aloud, Silence. Then the Patriarch holding his right hand upon his Head, ſpeaks aloud, ſo that all may hear, The Divine Grace which always makes ſound thoſe things that are weak, and compleats what's imperfect, promotes</hi> N. N. <hi>the moſt reverend Deacon to be a Prieſt: Let us therefore pray for him, that the grace of the All-Holy Spirit may deſcend upon him. Then again ſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him three times, and laying his hand upon his head; when the Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con has ſaid, Let us pray, the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch repeats that Prayer ſoftly, O God who art without beginning and without end &amp;c. After this follow the general Interceſſions, which when they are ended, or while they are repeating, the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arch laying his hand again upon his head as before, Prays to God to fill him with the gifts of his Holy Spirit, that He may be capable of doing all things belonging to his Function.</hi> I need not inſiſt upon other Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, the Perſon ordain'd having receiv'd his Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter before: Where it's obſervable, that as the <hi>Greek</hi> Church aſſigns the Office no otherwiſe but as the Church of <hi>England</hi> does, <hi>viz.</hi> by giving notice to the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:95912:11"/>
People, what Order the Perſon is Conſecrated to; ſo the <hi>Greek</hi> Church differs much from that of <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me,</hi> in the form of the Words uſed, which argues their opinion of the no neceſſity of ſuch a ſet Form, and conſequently that Orders are no Sacrament, as that word Sacrament is underſtood in the ſtricteſt Senſe by Eccleſiaſtical Writers: Yet <hi>Habertus</hi> is ſo far from ſuppoſing any <hi>deficiency in the</hi> Greek <hi>Church,</hi> that in Effect He charges <hi>the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>with Innovation;</hi> for he tells us,<note place="margin">Traditionis potius quam Scriptorum Authoritate conſtat. <hi>Pont. Gr. obſ. Hab.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>That the words us'd upon touching the Veſſels, are rather built upon Oral Tradition, than upon the Authority of any good Writers.</hi> He refers us to ſeveral Teſtimonies of the <hi>Greek</hi> Fathers, of greateſt Reputation, given to this Form, Originally us'd in their Church. He obſerves, that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> objected nothing to the <hi>Greek Rituals</hi> in the <hi>Florentine Council:</hi> He ſhews, that Ordination and Laying on of hands, when apply'd to Men, ſet apart for the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the Church, are the ſame thing: That there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in their Eccleſiaſtical Writers, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, all ſignifying <hi>Laying on of hands,</hi> are all indifferently us'd for Ordination. He alledges that of the Writer <hi>De Eccleſiaſtica Hierarchia, That the Impoſition of the Biſhops hands,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>c.</hi> 5.</note> 
               <hi>gives both the Character and Authority of a Prieſt;</hi> and gives us withal ſuch an Inſtance of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence of the <hi>Roman</hi> See to thoſe of the <hi>Greek</hi> Communion in <hi>Italy,</hi> as muſt either prove their full ſatisfaction with the <hi>Grecian</hi> Prieſthood, or elſe that the <hi>Roman</hi> Biſhops have very little care of their good. It's the Decree of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> the Eighth, <hi>Let the Protector of the</hi> Greek <hi>Nation provide, that ſome Eaſtern Biſhop, conſecrated after
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:95912:12"/>
the</hi> Greek <hi>manner, reſide at</hi> Rome <hi>to perform Divine Offices,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Caret Protector, ut Graecus aliquis ex Oriente ritu Graeco conſecratus Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copus Romae ſit, ad Divina Officia at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que Ordinationes ritu Graeco peragen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das, qui quae ad Caeremonias &amp; ritus Orientalis Eccleſiae faciunt, docere alumnos poſſit, &amp; ipſe per omnia fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vet; Jurent queque Italo Graeci ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Eccleſiaſticum ac ſacros Ordines uſque ad Presbyteratum ritu Graeco ſuſcepturos, quandoque &amp; ubi Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioribus viſum fuerit. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and to Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain according to the</hi> Graecian <hi>Rites, who may be able to teach Novices thoſe things which belong to the Rites and Ceremonies of the</hi> Eaſtern <hi>Church, and may obſerve them ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly himſelf; and let the</hi> Greeks <hi>living in</hi> Italy, <hi>give Oath to take the Eccleſiaſtical Life, and Holy as Orders upon them, according to the manner of the</hi> Greeks, <hi>as far as the Order of Prieſthood, when and where their Superiours ſhall think fit:</hi> Which is not only a fair atteſtation to the validi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the <hi>Grecian</hi> Orders, but ſeems to imply the <hi>Greeks</hi> diſſatisfaction with the <hi>Roman</hi> Hierarchy, and a ſtrange kind of Condeſcenſion in the Univerſal Biſhop, to recede from his own Rights, and to give leave to a ſuppos'd Schiſmatical Clergy, to increaſe and thrive within his Juriſdiction. And <hi>Romaniſts</hi> have ſufficient reaſon to acquieſce in this Liberty of theirs, if what <hi>Father Goar,</hi> in his Notes upon the <hi>Euchology</hi> informs us be true, That <hi>Impoſition of Hands is not only an Adjunct of Holy Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Neque enim Comes eſt ſolùm &amp; ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventitia, non Integrans tantum &amp; ex decentia requiſita, ſed intrinſeca omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no neceſſaria &amp; eſſentialis Materia; quâ adhibitâ ſicut olim Apoſtoli, prout in eorum Actis &amp; Scriptis legimus Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conos Presbyteros &amp; Epiſcopos creâ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt, abſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> illâ pariter nullum in ſubli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miores Hierarchiae Eccleſiaſticae gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus ſucceſſores Epiſcopi poſſunt evehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re. <hi>Goar. in Euch.</hi> p. 256.</note> 
               <hi>or meerly adventitious, not only an Integral part, or a thing requir'd for Decencies ſake; but that it's wholly the Intrinſical neceſſary and Eſſential Matter of them; by which as the Apoſtles of old created Deacons, Presbyters and Biſhops, as appears by their Writings, and the Hiſtory of their Acts; ſo without that, the Biſhops who ſucceed them, can raiſe no Man to Superior Orders
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:95912:12"/>
in the Sacred Hierarchy.</hi> And as he tells us after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, <hi>If we examine the Euchology never ſo ſtrictly, we ſhall find no other matter of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders ſo much as once mention'd,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cum in Univerſâ Eccleſiâ unam Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentorum adminiſtrandorum ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem eſſentialem (materiam nimirum &amp; formam) ſtatuere neceſſe eſt, nec in Graeca illius portione, alia quam ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Impoſitio queat aſſignari; Indubie ſequitur, in Latinâ eandem quoque eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentialem eſſe reputandam. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>but Impoſition of Hands;</hi> and his Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence from all is very remarkable, and much againſt the now prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Tenet of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, <hi>That ſince it's neceſſary there ſhould be ſome one Eſſential Rule or Method of diſpenſing Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Orders in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Church, and that there can be no other Matter of Orders aſſign'd in the</hi> Eaſtern <hi>parts of that Church, but only Impoſition of Hands; it muſt follow without Diſpute, that even in the</hi> Latine <hi>Church, the ſame excluſive of all other Ceremonies, is Eſſential to them:</hi> And to this Opinion of his, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks that of <hi>St. Chryſoſtome</hi> agrees very well, who tells us in plain terms, <hi>This is Ordination, The Hand is laid upon the Man, but God Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates the whole,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Chryſ. in Act. Ap. Hom: <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and it's Gods Hand which touches the Head of the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon Ordained, if he be Ordained Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularly.</hi> If then all this be true, if we have indeed the concurrence of ſo large a part of the <hi>Catholick Church</hi> as the <hi>Greek</hi> is, and that the Form of words us'd by them, is no more Demonſtrative of the Order to be conferr'd, than ours in the Church of <hi>England</hi> was at the beginning of the Reformation; we can be no more deny'd, to have a <hi>Regular Succeſſion of Church Officers</hi> than they. And we may ſuppoſe, ſuch Conſiderations mov'd <hi>St. Clara, P. Walſh,</hi> and others of the <hi>Roman</hi> Communion, to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low our Orders as full and valid to all intents and purpoſes: But that we want a <hi>Power to offer other Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices,</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:95912:13"/>
than thoſe of Praiſe and Thankſgiving, is a Want no more intolerable in our Prieſts or Presbyters, than it was in the Apoſtles themſelves. And I have not yet heard of any Catholick Tradition, that either our Saviour us'd thoſe words, <hi>Receive thou Power to offer Sacrifices,</hi> &amp;c. to any Apoſtle; or that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles us'd it to any of thoſe whom they afterwards Commiſſion'd to Preach the Goſpel.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Our Orders then being valid, as to to their <hi>Eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tials,</hi> notwithſtanding that great <hi>Pretended defect;</hi> it will follow, that all that Charge laid upon our Church of Hereſy and Schiſm, can no way render them imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect or ineffectual: And if the <hi>Roman</hi> Doctrine of the <hi>Indelible Character</hi> be true, thoſe who aſſert that muſt for their own ſake defend our Church, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſince it's apprehended by ſome, as we obſerv'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that a denial of the <hi>Indelible Character</hi> would irrecoverably ruine the Sacrament. And ſuch indeed was the Doctrine of the Ancient Church, in which the <hi>Hereticks and Schiſmaticks</hi> are with all <hi>Severity</hi> prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited to <hi>ordain</hi> any, or to <hi>Adminiſter Sacraments;</hi> yet if they would ſtill without fear of <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Cenſure</hi> preſume to do ſuch things, their Actions were good, and in full force; Antiquity ſo concurring with that Common Law Maxime, <hi>Quod fieri non debet factum valet; That which of it ſelf, or ſo and ſo circumſtatiated, ought not to be done; yet when it is once done, ſtands good and irreverſible.</hi> I wonder not indeed that <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> tho given by <hi>Hereticks,</hi> ſhould be approv'd in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſince they allow <hi>Lay-men, Women, Perſons unbaptiz'd, nay,</hi> Jews <hi>or</hi> Turks <hi>to baptize in caſes of neceſſity:</hi> But in ſo doing, they ſeem much to forget a ſtanding Rule of their own, <hi>That none can give that to another, which he never had himſelf:</hi> For, as I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:95912:13"/>
they tell us, <hi>That Baptiſm is one of thoſe Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which imprint an indelible Character.</hi> Yet ſuch is the Doctrine of their great <hi>Aquinas.</hi> They deny indeed, that any can give Holy Orders, except Biſhops; but He who is once made a Biſhop, muſt continue ſo to his lifes end; nor can the Irregularity of his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, nor any Schiſm created by him in the Church, nor any Hereſy inveſted or propagated by him, take away that <hi>Epiſcopal Power</hi> perſonally inveſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in him, howſoever the <hi>Exerciſe of that Power,</hi> may be reſtrain'd by <hi>Civil or Eccleſiaſtical Conſtitutions;</hi> and conſequently thoſe capable of Orders, who are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated by ſuch Biſhops, are really <hi>Deacons, Prieſts, or Biſhops,</hi> according to the particular Character im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd on them: So we may find <hi>Arrian Biſhops</hi> Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daining others of equally <hi>Heretical Sentiments</hi> with themſelves; which Perſons ſo Ordain'd, if at any time they abjur'd their <hi>Heretical Pravity,</hi> were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd into the <hi>Orthodox Church,</hi> and admitted to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe the ſame Offices, they were formerly aſſign'd to, without <hi>Re-ordination:</hi> To this purpoſe we read in the <hi>Anſwers to the Orthodox,</hi> publiſh'd among the works of <hi>Juſtin Martyr, That the Crime of an Heretick re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning to the true Faith, if it had been only ſome falſe Opinion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Reſp. ad Orthod. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>was to be rectified by a change of Judgment, if it were an Error in Baptiſm, by Confirmation, if in Orders, by lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on of Hands;</hi> which laying on of Hands was no Reordination, but only a particular Ceremony, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the <hi>laps'd in time of Perſecution,</hi> as well as thoſe who had <hi>fallen into Hereſie, Laymen</hi> as well as <hi>Clergy Men,</hi> were readmitted into <hi>Catholick Communion:</hi> So
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:95912:14"/>
               <hi>Dionyſius of Alexandria, in Euſebius,</hi> tells us, <hi>That it was an Ancient Cuſtom,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Euſeb. Hiſt. Eccl. l. <hi>7.</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>that ſuch ſhould be receiv'd into the Church by Prayer, with laying on of hands;</hi> and <hi>Aurelius Biſhop of Carthage,</hi> deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining concerning the <hi>Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Dotaniſts,</hi> orders, <hi>That ſeeing it was not lawful to iterate that, which was to be given but once,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Conc. gen. T. <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>1083.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>if they heartily renounced that Error, they may be receiv'd into that one Church, the Mother of all Chriſtians, by laying on of hands:</hi> And the ſame care is taken in the <hi>Eighth Canon of the firſt Council of Nice,</hi> which is plain it ſelf, and ſo interpreted by <hi>Balſamon, Zonaras</hi> and <hi>Ariſtenus,</hi> and farther illuſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by our <hi>Learned Beverege.</hi> The ſame is atteſted on the part of the <hi>Latin</hi> Church,<note place="margin">Auguſt. cont. Epiſt. Par. <hi>l. 2. c. 13.</hi> Anaſtaſii <hi>2.</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtola ad Anaſt. Imp. de Acacio &amp; Acacianis. Conc. gen. T. <hi>4. c. 7. 8.</hi>
               </note> by <hi>St. Auſtin,</hi> in his anſwer to the Epiſtle of <hi>Parmenian the Donatiſt,</hi> and by <hi>Anaſtaſius, the Second</hi> of that Name, Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> in an Epiſtle to <hi>Anaſtaſius,</hi> Emperour of <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi> The care taken was only this; That the perſons ſhould be qualified according to the Canons of the Church, in that caſe provided, and that the Perſons ordaining ſhould be really Biſhops; which things being ſecured, the Ordain'd upon Readmiſſion to Catholick Communion, retain'd their Offices and Powers ſtill.</p>
            <p>To conclude this then, If Orders be no Sacrament in a ſtrict ſenſe; if the Eſſence of them conſiſt only in Impoſition of the hands of Biſhops; if the <hi>Greek</hi> and Antient <hi>Latin</hi> Church, and the moſt learned perſons of the <hi>Latin</hi> Communion, now agree in that Doctrine; if the Church of <hi>England</hi> in her firſt reform'd Rituals, gave as clear an Aſſignation to his particular Office
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:95912:14"/>
to the Perſon ordain'd, as either the <hi>Greek</hi> or <hi>Roman</hi> Church do at preſent; and finally, if real Hereſy or Schiſm, cannot annihilate Epiſcopal Sacerdotal power: The conſequence of all muſt be, <hi>That our Orders are ſtill good and valid, and the Eſtabliſh'd Church of</hi> England, <hi>ſo far at leaſt a true and ſound Member of the Catholick Church of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now it were no difficult Matter, to retort the Objection againſt our Adverſaries, and prove the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>validity of their Orders, upon the Principles and Practices of their own Church. For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. They tell us, <hi>That it's the Intention of the Prieſt, not the Form or Matter of Inſtitution, that makes the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:</hi> So that tho a Man be ordain'd a Prieſt or a Biſhop with all the Ceremonies of the Pontifical, and by a Biſhop with thoſe very words now made uſe of in the Exhibition of the Veſſels; yet if the Biſhop minds not what he's about, or intend not to do what the Church intends, the Ordain'd remains ſtill without either Character or Power, by which means if one Biſhop has but once fail'd in the Collation of Orders, they run down, for ought they know, <hi>in infinitum,</hi> without any due Conſecration; and ſince humane Frailties are ſo many, and the Artifices of Hell ſo inceſſant and prevailing, as we muſt needs have a great many Doubts naturally grow upon us, concerning the <hi>Intentions</hi> of thoſe whole lives we ſee <hi>Extravagant and Impious;</hi> ſo from thence we neceſſarily deduce an Infinity of Uncertaintys. If this <hi>Conceipt</hi> were only the <hi>Caprice of ſome wild Head,</hi> it were the leſs conſiderable: But it's the determination of their <hi>oraculous Council of Trent,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Si quis dixe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, in Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris, dum Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramenta conficiunt &amp; conferunt, non requiri intentionem ſaltem faciendi quod facit Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia, <hi>Anathema ſit. Seſſio.</hi> 7. <hi>Can.</hi> 11.</note> that <hi>If any ſhall ſay there is not required in Miniſters,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:95912:15"/>
while they Conſecrate and diſpence the Sacraments, an Intention at leaſt of doing what the Church does, Let that Perſon ſo ſaying be accurs'd:</hi> And the Annotators up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Plantin</hi> Edition of that Council, refers us to the Decrees of <hi>Eugenius</hi> the 4th. in the <hi>Florentine</hi> Council, where we are taught, <hi>That the Sacraments are perfected by three things; By outward Signs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Omnia Sacramenta tribus perſiciuntur, videlicet, Rebus tanquam Materia, Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis tanquam Forma, &amp; Perſona Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtri conferentis Sacramentum, cum intentione faciendi quod facit Eccleſia; quorum ſi aliquod deſit, non perficit Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentum. <hi>Inſtruct. ad Armenos. Conc. gen. T.</hi> 13. p. 535.</note> 
               <hi>as the Matter, by Words, as the Form; and by the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Miniſter diſpenſing the Sacrament, with an intention of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that which the Church does; of which three things, if any one be wanting, there can be no Sacrament.</hi> It were an eaſie work to confute this Opinion, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing both Unſcriptural and Irra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional;<note place="margin">Sacramenta miniſtrari poſſunt à bonis &amp; à malis, à fidelibus &amp; infidelibus, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fra Eccleſiam &amp; extra; quia ſi diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri poſſint tantum à bonis, nullus eſſet certus de ſuſceptione Sacramenti, cum nullus fit certus de bonitate Miniſtri, ſicut nec de propria, &amp; ita oporteret ſemper iterari, &amp; malitia unius praeju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicaret alienae ſaluti. <hi>Lindwood. Conſtit. prov.</hi> l. 1. <hi>tit.</hi> 7. <hi>gl. pro quibus citat B. Thom. Edit. Oxon.</hi> 1679. Intra Catholicam Eccleſiam, in Myſterio Corporis &amp; Sanguinis Domini, nihil à bono ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus, nihil à malo minus perficitur Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdote, quia non in merito Conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, ſed in verbo perficitur Creatoris &amp; virtute Spiritus Sancti. <hi>Decreti p.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 1. <hi>Qu.</hi> 1. <hi>citat. ex Auguſtino contra Epiſt. Parmen. l.</hi> 2.</note> and how it thwarts the Doctrine of ſome great Men of your own, may be ſeen by thoſe <hi>Paſſages in the Margin;</hi> but as they aſſert it, it is <hi>Argumentum ad Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines;</hi> the conſequence of which we know well enough, the <hi>Truth</hi> we ſhall leave them to make good as well as they can. But, if we look upon <hi>Conſecration to Church Offices</hi> only as an <hi>Holy Ordinance,</hi> but no <hi>Sacrament:</hi> We may then challenge the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> as introducing a <hi>Nullity</hi> in their Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, by ſo notorious a deviation from the Examples of <hi>Chriſt and his Apoſtles,</hi> from the Methods of the <hi>Ancient <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Church,</hi> and from their own <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentick Conſtitutions;</hi> to prove which Crime of theirs,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:95912:15"/>
we may recur to thoſe Authorities before inſiſted on: From which we learn, <hi>That Impoſition of Hands</hi> was the only Eſſence of Orders; that their modern Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies are meer Innovations, and, as by them us'd, ſhameful Corruptions of the firſt Inſtitution: For tho' we allow that <hi>Power to the Governors of every true Chriſtian Church,</hi> to add ſome ſignificant <hi>Ceremonies</hi> to a Divine Ordinance (provided they are neither <hi>Indecent, Superſtitious nor Troubleſome,</hi> and therefore might paſs by that <hi>addition of touching the Conſecrated Veſſels</hi> among other little <hi>Fooleries</hi> of that Church;) Yet ſince they have fixt <hi>the Eſſence of that Ordinance,</hi> in that touching of thoſe Veſſels, and have made Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of Hands, rather an <hi>impertinent Formality,</hi> than a matter of Neceſſity, as may appear from that of <hi>Gregory the Ninth, In fragmentis Decretalium;</hi> we cannot but conclude, that they have gone beyond all bounds of <hi>Juſt Eccleſiaſtical Authority.</hi> For in that Decree. as it's plain, that Impoſition of Hands is made a meer non-eſſential Circumſtance; ſo it infers a Power in perſons Ordain'd, to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute their Functions in all parts,<note place="margin">Presbyter &amp; Diaconus cum ordinantur Manus impoſitionem tactu corporali, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu ab Apoſtolis introducto, recipiunt; Quod ſi omiſſum fuerit, non eſt aliqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenus iterandum, ſed ſtatuto tempore ad hujuſmodi Ordines conferendos, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tè ſupplendum quod per errorem exti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tit praetermiſſum. <hi>Concil. general.</hi> T. 11. p. 384. c. 52. <hi>Epiſt. ad Archiepieſc. Lond. In margine vero decretalium melius legitur, Lugdunenſem.</hi>
               </note> as occaſion requires, without it; for it lays no prohibition on them, and yet orders the ſupplying of all defects only at Canonical times, the Interſtices of which, are long enough to admit various exerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>Diaconal or Sacerdotal Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</hi> Nor does the Gloſs upon this part of the Canon Law help the matter at all, though it be clog'd with a Superfaetation of Notes: For tho' the firſt be, <hi>That a Deacon and Presbyter ought to be Ordain'd by Impoſition of Hands;</hi> the ſecond, <hi>that
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:95912:16"/>
that manner of Ordination is deduc'd from Apoſtolical example;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nota 1. Quòd Presbyter &amp; Diaconus per manus Impoſitionem debet Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri. Item Nota. Quòd Ordinatio Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotis &amp; Diaconi, introducta eſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplo Apoſtolorum. Item nota, quòd idem eſt in parte quod in toto. Item, Quòd duo imperfecta faciunt unum per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectum. <hi>Decretal. Greg.</hi> l. 1. <hi>Tit.</hi> 16. c. 3. <hi>gl.</hi> p. 282. <hi>Edit. Lugd.</hi> 1671.</note> yet ſure it's concluded, that <hi>there's the ſame virtue in a Semi-Ordination, as in our Compleated, and that two Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfects makes one Perfect.</hi> We cannot deduce any thing from the whole, but <hi>That an Ordinance un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionably ſacred, and of Divine Original, is ſo far perverted by thoſe of the</hi> Roman <hi>Church, as to have loſt its Nature;</hi> which concluſion we may be the more confirm'd in, if we obſerve that Aſſertion of ſome Modern Caſuiſts, <hi>That where by any Miſtake it has ſo happen'd, that the Perſon to be Ordain'd, did not touch both the Patten and Chalice with that exactneſs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd by the</hi> Roman <hi>Rubrick;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bonacina. D. <hi>8.</hi> q. <hi>2.</hi> puncto <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>or where it is rationally doubted, whether they did touch them or not, there they ought to be Ordain'd again, the former Ceremonies being wholly Inſignificant:</hi> Which ſtrange Sleight of <hi>Apoſtolical Practice,</hi> and weight laid upon this <hi>new Invention,</hi> I can no way reconcile to that Poſition of <hi>Alexander Alenſis, Thoſe things which are order'd by Men, may be alter'd by Men; but thoſe which are inſtituted by God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Quae ab homine Ordinata ſunt, ab ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine poſſunt mutari, quae autem à Deo inſtituta ſunt, non niſi dictante Deo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent mutari. <hi>Alonſis Sum.</hi> p. 4. q. 9. <hi>Memb.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2. <hi>art.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>may not be chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed but by the Command of the ſame God.</hi> Beſides, as to Sacraments they tell us, <hi>They muſt be admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred</hi> In Forma Eccleſiae,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Decret.</hi> p. 2. c. 1. q. 1. c. 51. <hi>Hi qui</hi> c. 52. <hi>Si quis.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>or that otherwiſe they are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>effectual.</hi> What Church then muſt that be, according to whoſe Form Orders muſt be conferr'd? Muſt it be the Ancient or Modern Church of <hi>Rome?</hi> The Queſtion is Reaſonable, ſince they have varied from themſelves ſo much; for we can find no <hi>Weſtern Ritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al</hi> mentioning the Touch of the Veſſels, for the firſt
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:95912:16"/>
               <hi>Nine hundred years</hi> after Chriſt: If at laſt the Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Paſtors in the Church of God, be inſtituted by Chriſt and his Apoſtles; and if the manner how thoſe firſt Church-Governors collated Holy Orders, be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd on Sacred Writ: Then thoſe who have varied ſo much from their Preſcriptions, and yet pretend to confer the ſame Divine Grace ſtill, have to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of their Power evacuated both the Diaconal and Sacerdotal Offices within their own Church; and if urged ſeverely with their own Principles, muſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear at beſt but an <hi>Embryo, an unſhaped and incompleat Church, their Prieſthood, Sacraments and Government, falling at once to the ground.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. It's obvious to any to object to them, <hi>That Laying on of hands, without uſing any Words at all, whereby the meaning of that action ſhould be gueſt at, is a Ceremony of no Conſequence at all:</hi> Yet the very Eſſence of Orders, according to their <hi>Schoolmen</hi> before cited, conſiſts in ſuch a <hi>mute Impoſition of hands;</hi> by which it appears, That the Sacrament of Orders, as they call it, is of a very different Nature from all the reſt: For ſhould the Prieſt <hi>Anoint</hi> a Man with <hi>Oyl,</hi> tho in a <hi>Dying State,</hi> and ſay nothing; who would call it <hi>Extreme <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction?</hi> Who would dream that the Prieſt <hi>Baptiz'd</hi> every Man whom he ſhould <hi>Sprinkle Water on,</hi> unleſs he us'd the <hi>words of Inſtitution?</hi> And we conclude, That thoſe of the <hi>Roman Communion,</hi> would ſcarce believe the <hi>Bread and Wine Tranſubſtantiated into the Body and Blood of Chriſt, by the bare Contact of the Prieſts Hand,</hi> without thoſe powerful Words <hi>Hoc enim eſt Corpus meum;</hi> the words being as Eſſential to the Sacrament, as the Elements, or the particular action of the Prieſt. Now if a Biſhop lay his hand upon my Head, and ſay nothing, who knows whether it be to give me his
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:95912:17"/>
Bleſſing, to confirm me after Baptiſm, to Conſecrate me to ſome ſacred Employ; or whether it were not an action purely accidental, or a mark of ſome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal kindneſs to me? <hi>For a Biſhop, as a Biſhop,</hi> may intend by ſuch an action any one of theſe things, as well as Ordination: It's true, they have ſome <hi>cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtantials and appendages</hi> in their preſent <hi>Rituals</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrative enough, but thoſe may be omitted, and a <hi>perfectly mute Impoſition of hands</hi> be made uſe of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, as being only Eſſential to the thing deſign'd; for <hi>if the Eſſentials of an Ordinance be us'd, the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances can add nothing to its Perfection or Imperfection:</hi> So the <hi>Roman</hi> Church allows Baptiſm of Infants a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat Sacrament, when adminiſtred by ſuch perſons who have no Authority to Conſecrate the Elements, or by Prieſts in ſuch ſtreights of time, as render their Conſecration impracticable. If we ſhould grant what ſome would fain perſwade us, <hi>That Impoſition of hands, and touching the Veſſels, are both Eſſential to Ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi> Notwithſtanding this, As when they allow <hi>Bread and Wine</hi> both as <hi>Eſſentials</hi> to the <hi>Sacrament of the Lords Supper,</hi> yet they eſteem it enough, to admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter that Sacrament <hi>in one kind</hi> to all Communicants; ſo it may upon the ſame grounds be determin'd ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, to give Orders only by one Mean, the <hi>virtue</hi> of the other <hi>Eſſential</hi> being ſuppos'd to be in that one by <hi>Concomitancy:</hi> But a Ceremony wholly ſilent, is ſo very unintelligible to the vulgar, that though they could be brought to apprehend its general mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, yet unleſs there were ſo many <hi>different Modes of laying on of Hands,</hi> it were impoſſible for them to diſtinguiſh between Biſhops, Prieſts and Deacons, to the great trouble and diſſatisfaction of thoſe, who among a thouſand Doubts and Uncertainties, muſt
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:95912:17"/>
partake of the Ordinances of God by their hands: And this defect themſelves are ſo ſenſible of, that though Impoſition of hands be only a <hi>dumb Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance,</hi> yet when the <hi>Veſſels are exhibited,</hi> in which Action they now generally fix the Eſſence of Orders, the Biſhop ordaining uſes a <hi>particular Form expreſſive of the Office</hi> then conferr'd. But it is</p>
            <p n="3">3. Such a <hi>Form,</hi> as if well examin'd, would leave us more at a loſs for the validity of their Prieſthood, than all their precedent ſilence, <hi>Take thou Power,</hi> &amp;c. where it would give us very great ſatisfaction, if they would inform us, what kind of <hi>Sacrifices</hi> their Prieſts offer, Whether <hi>Typical, and ſo Carnal and Senſible,</hi> Or elſe <hi>Spiritual:</hi> If Spiritual, we know of none ſuch relating to their publick Duties, but Prayers and Praiſes, in their largeſt extent <hi>Spiritual Sacrifices in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, acceptable to God through Jeſus Chriſt:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.5.</note> We know of none concerning them in private, but ſuch as all Chriſtians may offer as well as Prieſts, <hi>Preſenting their Bodies a living Sacrifice, holy and acceptable to God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 12.1.</note> 
               <hi>which is their reaſonable Service.</hi> If their Sacrifices are <hi>Typical,</hi> by whom were they Inſtituted? Or what are they <hi>Types</hi> of? If of the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> to come, their <hi>Prieſthood</hi> muſt be either <hi>Judaic or Pagan,</hi> whoſe va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Sacrifices, either more expreſly, as command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by God, or more darkly, as taken up from <hi>Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Gratitude,</hi> or from <hi>Imitation,</hi> were their great expreſſions of their Hope of a <hi>Meſſiah</hi> to come, or of ſome extraordinary Proviſions of Immenſe Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, for the Worlds Redemption from that prodigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Corruption it was immerſt in: If their <hi>Prieſthood</hi> be ſuch, they muſt no more pretend to be an <hi>Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical,</hi> much leſs <hi>the one Holy Catholick Church.</hi> If their Sacrifices be <hi>Types of the Meſſiah already come,</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:95912:18"/>
they are the <hi>Propheſies of things long ſince paſt,</hi> and juſt as good Senſe. If they inſtance in the <hi>Sacrament of the Lords Supper,</hi> we believe that to be in <hi>Euchariſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Commemorative Sacrifice,</hi> of which as oft as we par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take worthily, we preſent a juſt Offering of Thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to God for the infinitely meritorious Death and Paſſion of our Saviour; and this Sacrifice is ſtill pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spiritual. But if they would perſwade us, That in <hi>that Euchariſt, the real, natural and ſubſtantial Body of the incarnate Son of God is broken as upon the Croſs: that the ſame Blood which then ran in his veins, is actually ſhed as by the Nails and Spear: That every Prieſt as oft as He conſecrates the Elements, does ſo break his Body and ſhed his Blood, and then offer them in Sacrifice to God the Father:</hi> We believe no ſuch Sacrifice can be now offered. The <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Sacrifices grew needleſs, when Chriſt had offer'd himſelf, not as they had been uſeleſs before, but as they had relation to him: As their Sacrifices were no longer requir'd, ſo no Prieſts were needful to attend them: And this is the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment us'd by the <hi>Author of the Epiſtle to the Hebrews,</hi> when having aſſerted the Imperfection of Judaic Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices, the impoſſibility that the Blood of Bulls and Goats ſhould take away ſin; he ſhows us how <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> (to whom he applies thoſe words of <hi>David, Sacrifices and Burnt Offerings thou wouldſt not, &amp;c.</hi>) takes away the uſe of thoſe Sacrifices, that he may evidence the abſolute neceſſity and validity of his own, by which be ſatisfy'd and accompliſh'd the will of God. <hi>By which will we are Sanctified, through the offering of the Body of Jeſus Chriſt once for all:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 10.10, 12, 14, 18.</note> Again, <hi>This Man after He had offer'd one Sacrifice for Sins, He ſate down for ever on the Right Hand of God.</hi> And, <hi>By one offering he has perfected for ever them that are ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:95912:18"/>
Now Chriſtians generally relieve, <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t Chriſt by this one offering of himſelf, obtain'd remiſſion of ſins for all them that Believe;</hi> and then the Apoſtles con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence is very natural, <hi>Where remiſſion of theſe is, there is no more offering for ſin, if no more offering for ſins, then none at all, and then no need of ſuch ſacrificing Prieſts.</hi> Nor has <hi>Eſtius</hi> at all prov'd the neceſſity of the Continuance of ſuch propitiatory Sacrifices, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding that great one of our Saviour upon the Croſs, who indeed was the only acceptable High Prieſt, who had power to offer ſo perfect a Sacrifice. It might be added, That the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>Incru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entum Sacrificium</hi> of the Antients agrees very ill with this <hi>Tranſubſtantiated Corporeal Sacrifice,</hi> but well enough with the notion of a <hi>Commemorative and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual one.</hi> We might urge that of the learned <hi>Oughtram,</hi> concerning the Eſſential difference between that of <hi>Aaron</hi> and the <hi>Evangelical Prieſthood.</hi> That <hi>Aarons</hi> office as a Sacrificing Prieſt, was to manage the affairs of Men with God, according to that of the Author to the <hi>Hebrews, Every High Prieſt taken from among Men is ordain'd for Men in things appertaining to God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 5.1.</note> 
               <hi>that he may offer both gifts and Sacrifices for men:</hi> Whereas the buſineſs of the Apoſtles and their Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors in the Miniſtry of the Goſpel, is to manage the buſineſs of God with Men, according to that of St. <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 5.20.</note> 
               <q>
                  <hi>We are Ambaſſadors of Chriſt, as tho God did beſeech you by us,</hi> we pray in Chriſts ſtead that you would be reconciled unto God: St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of himſelf as a real Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficing Prieſt, upon account of his <hi>offering up the</hi> Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles <hi>to God,</hi> who were acceptable becauſe <hi>Sanctified by the Holy Ghoſt;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 15.16, 17.</note> but in the ſame place he calls himſelf not the Miniſter of the <hi>Gentiles to Chriſt,</hi>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:95912:19"/>
but the Miniſter <hi>of Chriſt to the Gentiles;</hi> and therefore it's obſervable, That <hi>Evangelical Miniſters</hi> are no where in Scripture call'd <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,<note place="margin">Oughtram. de Sacriſ. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 19.</note> with relation to any ſuch <hi>Corporeal Sacrifices</hi> as the <hi>Jews</hi> offer'd, it not being the Miniſtry of the Apoſtles, but the Prieſthood of Jeſus Chriſt, that ſucceeded in the room of <hi>Aarons.</hi>
               </q> But the proſecution of theſe things would carry us too far beyond the bounds of the preſent Controverſie; only from the whole it will follow, <hi>That the Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficing Prieſts of the</hi> Roman <hi>Church, by deſerting the Commiſſion given by Chriſt to his Apoſtles, are indeed relaps'd into Judaiſm, or worſe: By which means their boaſted Succeſſion is quite broken off, to the ruine of their Churches Catholiciſm; if, as they tell us, a Succeſſion of Chriſtian Prieſts and Biſhops be one neceſſary mark of ſuch a Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now we have reaſon to admire the <hi>Goodneſs</hi> of <hi>Almighty God,</hi> who, as He made the <hi>Jews</hi> the bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt Enemies of our Saviour, the <hi>preſervers</hi> of thoſe <hi>Sacred Oracles</hi> which confirm'd his <hi>Meſſiahſhip,</hi> and by them, as <hi>Inſtruments,</hi> deliver'd down thoſe Holy writings to us <hi>Gentiles,</hi> to our <hi>Conviction,</hi> tho they had no ſuch effects upon that <hi>Obdurate People;</hi> ſo he has made the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> the <hi>Conveyancer</hi> of a <hi>Truly Apoſtolical Hierarchy</hi> down to us, tho they have almoſt loſt it among themſelves: They continue ſtill the <hi>Impoſition of Hands,</hi> though only as a <hi>Collateral and non-eſſential Ceremony,</hi> which we hope may have other <hi>Effect</hi> upon them, than what's agreeable to their own <hi>Miſtaken Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples:</hi> But ſince their abuſe or contempt of it, cannot alter the Nature of the thing it ſelf, We, deducing that Practice of <hi>Impoſition of Hands</hi> from
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:95912:19"/>
them, as they from <hi>the Apoſtles,</hi> and laying its due weight upon that <hi>Apoſtolical Inſtitution,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Additions or Alterations: We enjoy that <hi>Ordinance full and compleat</hi> among our ſelves, and enjoy that Succeſſion really, which they have ſo long Impertinently boaſted and valued themſelves upon.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
